so these are some more
questions that have come from around the world and
that have come from around the world and
some comments from youtube on youtube
i'll just read out someone's from
someone's comment from youtube
he says i was thinking this this person
said something i heard
and i didn't like
this person
did something i saw and i didn't like
but without my eye or my ears or this
body i wouldn't be able to experience
that person
so do i hate this person or do i really
hate my eye my ear or this body
the world outside of this body is only
experienced through this body
so how can it be outside
and how can i conceive outside of this
body if it's not on the basis of the
same body and senses
this is where the misconceiving happens
isn't it yeah
exactly that's exactly what it happens
that's where the buddha described
the sense organs
as
hollow empty without a substance
empty without a substance
in other words they don't appear
you don't you can't see your eye
so that's why you naturally then
think you hate that which you've seen
because there is nothing else there that
you can visibly hate
but actually what you are averse to
is the the
that negative uh sense base
negative uh sense base
that's hollow empty if a man is able to
say remember to look closely they will
find no substance to it it's just devoid
of so it's this basically a negative
space of you that's what your eye is
that which is which doesn't appear where
your sights are there
but it's the reason for your sights so
that's why it takes knowledge first take
sense restraint to stop acting towards
what you see
hear smell taste touch
stop fortifying the wrong notion that
that's what you are reversed to
and then you discover that
natural aversion natural patiga towards
these senses because they were always
the untamed animals not the objects they
were seeking
but even then you will not see the eye
as an object oh now i recognize you but
you get to know that through withdrawal
from the sense objects that i used to
chase for with likes or dislikes
what i'm left with now is that pure
aversion to the fact that there is
seeing there that undermines me that i'm
subjected to it would have said himself
like sight sounds melted such as agreeable
sight sounds melted such as agreeable
and disagreeable
they're uh besetting they're attacking
your senses
that's what sides do so to speak
so so you realize that it's your own
senses that that's where the problem is but for
that that's where the problem is but for
as long as you haven't been withdrawn
from the sense objects if you haven't
stopped acting towards the person that
upset you acting out
you will be maintaining the notion that
that's what the problem is and that's
exactly the root misconceiving like you
don't see
uh your body for what it is these sense
organs that actually you you resist
and that's why you delight in sense
objects of agreeable kind and that's why
you reverse to the sense objects of
disagreeable kind
because fundamentally you you don't want
to have to deal
you don't want to face that that that
voidness of those sense of sense organs
that the lack of substance that because
it reveals like non-ownership
if you were to see the eye truly for
what it is as a sense base because of
which there are sites
you realize it's inaccessible to you
any sense of control you had
preferences for pleasing avoiding this
pleasing side all that was completely
circumstantial on the basis you are
fully trapped within it
and exactly there is an outside of it
what you see is your eye seeing
so you develop this notion the knowledge
of the world outside because of which
you feel like
you freed yourself from these pressure
of these
five senses five sense organs the body
uh but that's the wrong notion and for
as long as you maintain the wrong notion
you're never gonna take on
that pressure correctly and you will not
be able to free yourself from it
so your senses are sort of open for
attack you know your sense yeah you're just
you know your sense yeah you're just
kind of and you can't how do you protect
that it's like that's what i mean they're
it's like that's what i mean they're
completely inaccessible to you
you can't you don't even have a say in
how senses see things or hear things
you only get the result of it and
and
for as long as you as i said don't
sufficiently withdraw yourself from
sense objects you will entertain a
degree of notion of control over sense
obviously because senses don't appear
these sense bases you can't see them i
cannot see itself ear cannot hear itself
so it's negative hollow empty all those
things that the suit is described with
and because of that all you see is you
and me
and this anger
or
whatever this pleasing thing in me and
this this pleasure so it's for me it's
mine i want it i don't want it but you
are completely outside of that whole
relationship between that eye that's
being harassed and besetted by these
sites and so on
but for as long as you don't withdraw
yourself from sidetransmitted touches
you will not see that there is something
else there that doesn't appear on that
level that that background the
pressuring body for what it is what i
was describing the natural patiga that
you discover it's like oh that's where
it is so would you say that you can
perceive them can you perceive the
senses no you can know them you get to
by by not misconceiving the perception
on account of them you get to understand
the nature of perception in other words
you get to understand the nature of
those hollow negative senses devoid of
substance that you cannot perceive you cannot see
that you cannot perceive you cannot see
directly that's why that whole point of
discerning the peripheral context and
everything else because if you expect
you're going to see a limit of what your
eyes are that's again that's not going
to be nowhere near
and they would have said that if a man
were to to examine those those sense
base and he compared him to those empty
rooms like a empty village the man escapes the
like a empty village the man escapes the
vipers and so on and comes to an empty
village and it's just devoid of anybody just
and it's just devoid of anybody just
empty and hollow and that's what the
senses are they just devoid
of presence and you realize oh
this is already abandoned this cannot be
owned that's already the nature of your sense
that's already the nature of your sense
basis
but most people wouldn't even get near
that to see it because most people would
not be sufficiently withdrawn from the
sense objects and that's where the
problem is
keeps you basically external to yourself
the assumption
by being engaged with the sense objects
not necessarily even just through core
centrality in general
the view is that oh you are outside
you can get outside you can choose and
do things outside
but actually all you can do is engage
with your senses that see things hear
things smell things and so there is an
outside of this body so this this notion
of
myself my identity
my identity
that thought is in is here
in this section of perception this area
and where where is the body where is the
senses which i am
identified with
i can't contact those things
no no everything everything is the
result of having them already
that's what i mean you can never step
outside and take the ownership or
protect them or choose what you can only
tame them or follow where they want to
take you there's no absolute there's no
third alternative that you can do
because it's all that on that internal
level so the first thing you need to do is
so the first thing you need to do is
stop misconceiving
those senses
that undermine you as as oh yes yes this
is my eye and this is my ear you
basically you're misconceiving them
uh through the external
means and criteria that you developed on
a kind of already misconceiving them
that's why you develop this perception
of external world and sense of control
and ownership and delight and and and
sensuality it's because you're already
misconceiving the senses for what they
are now on account of that misconceiving
you develop the view about external
world through which now you think you
can access this senses so it's like a
double sort of misconceiving
and when people look like oh yes this
the eye is just this medical thing and
stuff yeah when you look at it
not as that because of which there is
looking personally you can never see internally
personally you can never see internally
i the same way you're dissecting it in
in a lab or something
that's an object
that i can see because of these eyes
that are not objects not on the level of
the objects if these eyes become on the
level of the
object i will not have my sight anymore
so you can look at look at them you know
as a as a doctor scientist can
look at an eye and see how it works
but you need to see that that
you are accessing that through your own
eyes already which means it can never be
that uh internal counterpart that sense base
uh internal counterpart that sense base
that's always internally
how do you know that it's there
how do you know that it's there by
withdrawing yourself from sight sound
small test touches that otherwise please
or displease you by not acting towards
them then what do you find well you find
that empty hall of space you find that
empty village that everybody talks about
you realize yeah this hollowness is that
body because of which
i i was confusing myself to be the
conceiver and perceiver and owner and
master of the world
yet it's because of that this absolutely
unownable empty abandoned village that
everything has fled from because it's
subject to ruin
so then you will not entertain the
notion that you are the perceiver and
conceiver of the world
because you just saw that notion being
completely undermined and dismantled
and there is a certain another says that
it's because of that i the one is the
perceiver and conceiver of the world
because he doesn't understand the eye
so he becomes uh yeah i see this i
perceive this i can see this
because as i said there's nothing else
that appears there in that pop in those
palpable terms
so that's why a person needs to develop
internal to recognize these these
negative counterparts as necessary basis
but practically speaking what you're
going to find is just this unity of your
body experienced internally
whereby the the external thoughts that
you might have in regard to that body in
regard to the eye and ear are seen
second to the internal experience of the body
to the internal experience of the body
internally as a hollow empty
vessel thoughts are actually seen as external
thoughts are actually seen as external
yeah you cannot get rid of the thoughts
i shall not i must not think the eye if
i try to see the eye you will think the
eye but you should not conceive your
thought of the eye
to be that eye that is internally there
as that negative hollow empty vessel
empty room empty village
so training in regard to that that
internal negative space for the lack of
better word
uh
will then unpervert the order
of your thoughts in regard to the eye
and that which the i base actually is it
will remove the base for conceiving
then yes you will have the thoughts
about the eyes they were never the
problem but you will not carry they will not
but you will not carry they will not
carry the assumption that yes those
thoughts which basically external
and about external things
are my eyes
now eyes are that internal hollow
unownable subject to ruin village that
everybody has fled fled from
those that's your body those are your
senses so if if you if you're able to see that
so if if you if you're able to see that
way
the conceivings will fade away
you will not have to then make the
effort to stop conceiving or
misconceiving because
you realize oh no this is subject to you
know flooding and attacks and stuff i i
better not be there
and and that's how you free yourself
from it you can't free yourself from it
by pulling your eyes out
uh you can feel yourself by completely
removing any misconceived notion of
ownership in regard to the sights and the eyes and
in regard to the sights and the eyes and
both and everything else in between they
used to exist
being stuff you felt on account of sight
sounds meltdowns touches act things you
did choices you made intentions thoughts
you had all of that
on the result of that basis
so
we had another question about memories
where where are memories stored you know
where are memories stored you know
where's the mem where's the memory of
yesterday and the day before
where is that well at the same place
where the uh thoughts and images of that
question come from
so where the memories start where are
these designations that i'm using to ask
you a question where is that stored
and then you realize it's not it's it's
kind of an invalid question because it
assumes an external point of view that
can see the storage of my basically
consciousness and thoughts and
everything else and you cannot conceive
that well you can misconceive that as i
said assuming the outside of yourself is only
assuming the outside of yourself is only
like basically
can only be a form of misconceiving so
the notion of external
storage or whatever else it's very much
on the basis of your internal that comes
first and that's the point
and that's the point
so you can have those thoughts
so i must stop thinking this but you
must stop misconceiving the order you
must stop putting the thought of
external first the thought in regard to
the external sense object first the
meditation techniques about sense
objects and limiters and visions stop
putting that first and start discerning
that negative basically empty abandoned
sense sense organ body
as internal as that basis
that is what you're bound with there is
an outside of it
all the external perceptions and notions
and designations and thoughts and
questions you might have is within that
internal body you're bound with
but then
so the point is not to really figure out
uh get information or try and find
you know get hold of the eye get hold of
the ears and really understand how they
were but people would would still hold
the view that they can and that and it's
about that
but that's why it will never it your own
girl basically get frustrated and you
will not find the answer because yeah
it's based on the wrong premise so you
know me like
there is the mind there is mind objects
and there's mind consciousness and then
the coming together of the three's
context so how does it come together and
why does it come together and where is
the mind where's the objects exactly
situated but that's but you can't
but that's but you can't
to try and figure that out you can come
up with some fancy ideas
but that's not not the point that
description seems to me to be
enough it is it's not it's it's it's
it's not about figuring out the
relationship of those things it's about
just not
falling into the trap of misconceiving
and becoming the owner of it that's why
the all the interpretations of that
description came later did not come from
the buddha
you know what how that meeting occurs
like slapping of the hands and the sound
is the result that's not from the
suitors it's
it's
literally there in the world
the hollow village that gets attacked
every now and then and the result of
that attack is basically the pressure
that that that you can feel
on account of seeing smelling tasting
touching that's agreeable disagreeable
it's pulling you in the directions
how it happens it's irrelevant because
the fact is that you run that you cannot
remain unmoved that's your problem
contact has to cease not by removing the
village or that which comes into village
to attack it but by removing your bother
by it
so that's where the only way to know the
eye to know the object correctly is
first to see that you can only know them
on the basis of pressure already being
there you're a secondary and it's kind
of a secondary place you have no access
to those things no no control or
anything and then pressure is the
measure of you know whether you
understood it or not but you're trying
to get rid of it through finding answers
or you're able to endure it and see
through it and then remove basically
that patiga towards that internal aspect
and then whatever comes it will just
come through so to speak
you will not be bothered by it
but if people already have the view and
most of them would of that external
explanatory oh this is what happens
as that as if that's relevant to the
fact that you're pressured by the
pleasing and pressured by the
displeasing that's the if that's the
core that's the meeting spot
and now you're going to go and solve out
how this meeting happens by abandoning
the meeting spot and investigating sort
of theoretical aspects of it no the only
way to solve to undo the contact is to
endure it through where it is
and even though like the prerequisite
for the right view was the would have
said to
restrain yourself
from falling into seeking answers for
who am i what was i in the past will i
be in the future all these external
answers that pertain to the core of your
sense of self because that takes the
sense of self for granted and it also
assumes it externally by thinking i can
find the answers for it externally
and if a person needs to recognize yes
sense of self is a problem it's the root
of suffering and so on but i must
refrain myself from seeking these
questions out there so if you refrain
um
that that pressure to find these answers
which is always rooted in trying to get
rid of the pressure by the way but if
you refrain from seeking these external
answers and stay with the problem on
that internal level that's the that's
pretty much the first step that's the
correct step that's where sense
restraint always comes first and you
know as we spoke before like if somebody
something upsets you
you have to stop acting towards that
thing because otherwise you will never
see that that thing was never the root
of your upset even your internal craving
in regard to what you internally felt
in regard to the internal base that has
perceived something externally which is
within the internal base because you
cannot actually have something
externally independent independently
accessed or perceived independently of
the your or your sense organ so all you can
your or your sense organ so all you can
perceive is sense organ seeing or
hearing or smelling and touching so
there's no outside of it
there is no outside of it means already
there is no assumption of me being
outside and accessing outside so that's
already shrinking of atavada and so on
but that takes effort it's not about
finding the answer it's about actually
enduring that pressure to seek and
resolve the issue of myself and what i
am and who i am and where it came from
or the issue of the contact to resolve
it on that external plane
because that's already a perverted order
and you're looking in the wrong place
and feeding the perversion of the order
so
if you become then mindful of the body
in this way where you internally you
understand yeah you stand you don't have
access to the
body so you can become mindful of the
body internally
by not
falling into a trap
of putting the thoughts of your body
as that which your body is
so i say be mindful of the body the
first thing you want to have is an image
of your body
and that's fine
through that image of the body there is
the internal physicality of that body
being there that's the base of
mindfulness seeing body within the body
but the problem is that
people expect some magical result out of
it
and then they fail to look at the fail
to see that the actual problem is it's
just that this is what you put first
nothing else there
do you put that physicality of the body
see even physicality of the body is a
form of thought
and that can become form of
misconceiving then that's the mula parya
suta you misconceive the form one way or the
you misconceive the form one way or the
other
and that's what the practice is
you recognize the thought
you don't take it for granted as oh
that's what my body is because it is an
external thought in regard to that
physicality through the enduring of the thought
through the enduring of the thought
through the enduring of that contact
pressure you
you
you develop yourself to that counterpart
of physicality that is there because of
which you wouldn't you know otherwise
you wouldn't even have that thought
there so mindfulness of the body fine even
so mindfulness of the body fine even
have a thought of your posture or
whatever if you just sit down mindfully
if you just sit down mindfully
you are already aware that you are
seated that's already an image in your
mind and that's fine through that image
now discern the more actual physicality
of the seated body
without again perverting the order by
allowing new thoughts
to just take you into assumption that oh
yeah see that's what's happening because
of which this body is here no this body
is here because his body is here every
thought you have in regard to it is
within it not other way around
and that was the also like the problem
with like sensation watching and
meditation sensation is ultimately an external
sensation is ultimately an external
point of view that you keep applying to
your body
with the assumption that that's what's
internally felt but it's not let's touch
the touch it's a sense of touch sure so
there's not no problem like oh i feel
sensation in my back or something
but it's an external
i'm being touched there basically
even if it's inside of the body that's
not the agita internal aspect
which is on the level of the organ
body as an organ that can be touched
and that cannot be measured by
sensations that is a negative hollow
empty village
so if people have a view that sensations
measure the presence of the body and the
mindfulness of the body they're
basically using sense objects to measure
the presence of their organ which is
impossible which is already a form of
misconceiving because that's exactly why
people don't see their organs because
they put the sense objects first
and that's why no one's
mindful of the body there no but because
then when you look for the body you
expect to find it on the level of sense
objects because that's what your view
tells you it is there
and then you might be refining your
sense objects refining the perceptions
of touch into these subtle sensations
that's still external they will always
remain external and it's not a problem
to have those things the problem is that
you put that first and the actual
physicality of the body that is the
container of the most refined sensations
you must have you might have
is actually first and you don't see it
as first well you might you probably
don't even see it at all if you see it
you see it a second you you experience
it a second but then what what what you
what you would think that
that internal body is then
internal body is then
if you haven't experienced it
you can only you only think of it as
a perception of something
which means if it if i experience it
means i perceive it on some some level
yes but it's not a perception so but see
saying i can't perceive it is another
perception so you cannot not perceive it
either that's why the whole point of
mula para asute is not to not have
thoughts in regard to the body is just
to not misconceive the body on account
of those thoughts in other words all you
can do is withdraw yourself from the
perverting the order through your
thoughts and what you're left with
is the physicality of the body seeing
correctly unperverted order
unperverted order
and and body for what it is body there
and that's the body the body witnessing
that the buddha would describe as a part
of meditation
if you do if you if you do this practice
you can't
expect something you can't have an idea
something you can't have an idea
well you might be expecting something
but don't put that first
leave it second on account of the
physicality that you're doing internally
that is hollow empty unownable subject
to peril
and if that's if you're seeing your own
basis like that you will lose passion
towards any prospects and objects that
kind of existing within it so keep
seeing the thought of the body as
secondary yes and then when you say okay the
yes and then when you say okay the
thought of the body second this body is
first you recognize that's a thought
fine let it endure and through that
learn how to discern the physicality of
that body without making it into a new
object a new thought
that's that peripheral awareness we keep
talking about that you can infinitely
practice and all it does it's not to take you to
and all it does it's not to take you to
some special place at the end of the
peripheral planes no
all he does is eventually eradicates
your your casual ignorant habit of
perverting the order that's it if you
stay sufficiently on the
uh on the extent necessary of that
peripheral step in stepping away correctly
step in stepping away correctly
any tendency to flip back the order into
the wrong way will will be eradicated
and then we should like as the buddha
said inside
or they simply practice mindfulness of
the body to the extent necessary for the
final knowledge to become established
that's all
and yeah it's a very like you know it's
all lots of information theoretical and
so on but listen and really listen it's
a very practical thing
first you need to be thoroughly
restrained in terms of your actions by
body by speech by mind because each time
you act
out of greed aversion or distraction
you you pervert the order you reinforce
already perverted order you feed it you
keep throwing fuel on that burning fire
you stop acting you guard your sense
doors and then you're gonna start
discerning that
negative empty hollow emptiness village
emptiness sunyata this is empty
and you will not necessarily this is the
eye this is you can just see it in the
most generic terms of the body but you
will not
external perceptions will be seen for
what they are and that internal sense of
emptiness will be then seen at that's
that same space that i have no outside
of so the practical uh practical way of
of practicing mindfulness once you've
been thoroughly restrained
because if you're not that's your
practice of mindfulness a thought or
restraint uh guarding of the sense
though moderation eating watchfulness
then if you want to do more on top of
that you just do the same but but this
have already gathered
so to speak
but your sense restraint and effort into
its you know ceiling virtue and growing
on account of it but that has gathered
you realize okay so now i'm not leaking
outside i'm not spilling outside
my behavior has been restrained so when
i have the thoughts of the body
you can actually allow it to endure and
within that see the present physicality
because of which this thought is there
so you can never get to the pure
physicality because that's a thought
if you start like coming to it as an
object the only way to objectify it is
through having an image of it
which means physicality has been
misconceived so all you have to do is stop trying to
so all you have to do is stop trying to
access it through the assumption of
access and just see what's there and
stop putting the thoughts first
let them endure and then
discern the negative physicality
underneath it
and that's that's pretty much um like
practice well that's kind of the
combination of the first genre of the
level of withdrawal but your practice of
first john as we said before starts by
not acting
restraining your speech
guarding your sense doors you're already
gathered again
and that's why in first genre you would
have thought thinking and pondering you
know picking up the content and
whichever way people translate without
but the order will remain unperverted
if you're not established in the
physicality of that body if you have not
sufficiently stopped misconceiving it
and putting it second and putting the
thoughts as more fundamental
every time you have itaka
it comes from the outside
as that which is first because each time
the thought appears
unless as i said you have been developed
to the extent necessary it will come
with at least that initial perversion of
order that's the people who have developed
that's the people who have developed
genres in the suit as it said like oh
they're able to purify the thought in
its arising in other words in the
arising of the thought order will remain
unperverted there will be no pollution
so it's it's it's sustaining that order
and you can start sustaining that order
in a broader sense
the order of sense restraint the the
order of the aggregate of virtue
that becomes first now see virtue is not
first either
acting out is first
then you pondered and you understood
that you need to be restrained and now
you start actually preventing yourself
from putting the acts of non-virtue
first making them factual
making them factual
and if you've been counted within virtue
sufficiently enough for a period of time
you start to physically recognize and
aggregate the virtue and aggregate of
certain non-behavior
that you cultivated and now that's first
and if you choose to break it
now you realize ah that would be
perverted the order they'll be going
against the right order
and then same with speech and then
eventually you can do that on the level
of thoughts because that's where the
conceivings happen
that's where you pervert the fundamental
order and put the thought the image of
your body first not the physicality of
the body
and that's the whole
the um
well yeah the whole mother pariah suta
how one misconceives but there are other
suitors as well about that
when there is a contact they have a
thought of the body there is the latigas
aspect of it and there is the adiwan
aspect of it there is the resistance
aspect of it and there is the
designation aspect of it that's the core
of every contact
and usually it's a designation that's put
usually it's a designation that's put
first
they're simultaneously there it's not
the designation comes later
so thought of the body doesn't come
later that thought of the body is there
with the body which is why you know it's
the body
so thought designates that resistance
ambiguity that batiga
but it cannot go outside and possess it
or be separate to it yet that's what
every misconceiving carries implication
that that's the body already you put the
body second and you stop seeing fatigue
of the body for what it is
so that's the resistance contact
translating the sutra sometimes and the
designation contact
the two aspects of the same thing
and that's where the perversion happens
within that pressure of contact so that
for me you have to stop acting you have
to be able to endure the pressure of the
contact pleasant and unpleasant and then
within that see the physicality of it
simultaneously present with the thought
of the physicality of it
and don't prefer that or allow it to
endure and keep sustaining it and
protecting it
and then you can think freely
without any misconceivings without any
underlying tendency finding weight back
and that's basically thinking and
pondering of the first genre and when
the body is there unified how the sudden
will say the pleasure of their
unification is there that whole thing
because you're fully withdrawn and no
amount of thinking can pervert the order
and there is a sense of safety on
account of the profound sense of safety
because the threat was not that there
was a village
of empty kind that being harassed and
attacked the threat was that you didn't
know how to leave it
the threat was that you were there and
now you were not there anymore you
removed the ownership this right order
that you're speaking about
you're speaking about now right order
that's the right view
the right yes that's the right view
that's yeah and without the right view
of what the right order is you will not
even know what the right daughter is to
look for yeah but you can so someone can
get an idea of that yeah follow that
idea and you will get the right view
or remember that idea remember that idea
have an accurate memory of that idea
keep on remembering keep on remembering
but obviously that idea will not have
anything to pertain to and be recognized
as factual
unless your behavior has provided
sufficient basis for it
so your behavior needs to be purified
before it just remains theoretical it
remains theoretical and pondering but
you will not see it for yourself because
there is no matching physicality of it
of the right order everything you live
on a day-to-day basis is through the
perverted order so you can have all the
thoughts you want about the right order
unless your basic physical behavior
starts to emulate the right order there
is no basis for any of that to take root
you cannot practice the right order
while you allow yourself to keep
engaging in the wrong order by that
which is even more fundamental than you
thought action by body and by speech
so it's just not negotiable but you
realize actually it's good news as i
said before then all you have to do is
keep body restrained keep your speech
restrained and you're practicing you're
practicing the journey you're practicing
the right order you're practicing
towards the right view
and then your thoughts will have much
more further basis
even fleeting little thoughts if they
are correct are going to be recognized
instantly because the basis is there
so that's even when we said oh just
think about buddha dhamma sangha the
collection of virtue you'll get samadhi
as a result of it because yeah the body
behavior by body and by speech has been
purified and that aggregate still
persists now just tweak your thinking a little
now just tweak your thinking a little
bit focus on certain themes and pleasant
abiding here and now
that's what it also means by the way in
the suttas when buddha said mindfulness
should remain always
basically established upon the body
and never abandon
the body in terms of your satin
recollection as if somebody's going with a sword
as if somebody's going with a sword
behind you and you're carrying that pot
full of water and everything is trying
to distract you it's not about focusing
on the sensations and it's about
maintaining the right order never
slipping from it so establish the right
order of the body to that extent
necessary and don't allow it to be
perverted even if there are dancers
around you and everything else because
your head will be chopped off if you
prefer the order if you lose the
mindfulness of the body if you lose the
correct recollectedness of the body the
correct memory the memory that's that
doesn't prevent the order of the right
memory of the right order
so this is a
short suitor and it seems to be in
connection with what we're talking about
you know i think you've probably already
answered this
but maybe you could say something more
it starts because when what exists
by assuming what by adhering to what
does the thought occur i am superior i
am equal or i am inferior where where
so
the buddha says when there is the i
because by assuming the i by adhering to
that assumption of the eye the thought
occurs i am superior i am equal i am
inferior and so on with the ear nose
tongue body and mind
so this so
by assuming what in terms of the senses
does one start to get this by assuming
the wrong order
a sense of uh yeah that's what i mean by
assuming the externals first you don't
even see the internal you don't see the
eye you don't see so you are the
perceiver the conceiver which means you
are now comparable there i am better i
am worse i am equal but the point is no
you are secondary
and if you see yourself a secondary
there is no more conceit of superiority
or inferiority no you're out of the
picture you don't exist for the eye or
for the objects
you're irrelevant
so you can't even be dejected on account
of it because rejections requires some
recognition of you
being sort of you know demoted or
inferior yeah
and you there is no room for any conceit
because conceit comes as a result of
conceiving but i'm not equal then what
is this well you're not even equal
because even equality we are equals
requires me and you
but if both you and i are utterly
completely invisible to our own eye and sense of
invisible to our own eye and sense of
irrelevant non-existent
redundant then it's like well it's like
comparing two things that are redundant
you wouldn't say oh they're equal
they're just both equally redundant
maybe
so yeah conceit you can take that as i
said before it's it's more of a symptom
conceit is a symptom of a problem
now i must get rid of the conceit no i'm
yeah you must stop misconceiving
basically the core of your existence you
i mean like pride prizes yeah yeah right
right that's what i mean superiority
superiority yeah it's like a that i'm
better i'm worse i'm inferior all of
that is the result of the problem that
you're taking for granted
and so if you if you start as i said
sense restraint virtue and then look for
the correct practice of mindfulness of
the body that right order your conceit
will fail doesn't matter how you might
come across to other people the point is
internally there is no ana that
anatimani that he says in the like free
from any arrogance and so on it's not
there because that's the result of of
sustaining that wrong order and wrong
conceiving where you are the perceiver
the conceiver of the world which
inevitably then results in in you know
creating a certain value around that one
better i can get even better and so on
and there's a
uh i think this was from the terrigata
anyway this is uh
this is uh
this
arahant really his name is genta he's
the priest the high priest son it was
called and this is his poem
and this is his poem
in the terrigata
i was drunk with the pride of birth
and wealth and authority i wandered
about intoxicated with my own gorgeous
body no one was my equal or my better or so i
no one was my equal or my better or so i
thought
i was such an arrogant fool stuck up
waving my own flag
i never paid homage to anyone not even
my mother or father
nor others esteemed as respectable
i was stiff with pride lacking regard
for others
when i saw the foremost leader the most
excellent of charioteers
shining like the sun at the fall of the
mendikan sangha i discarded conceit and
vanity and with a clear and confident heart i
and with a clear and confident heart i
bowed down with a head to the most
excellent of all beings
the conceit of superiority and the
conceit of inferiority
have been given up and eradicated the
conceit i am
is cut off and every kind of conceit is
destroyed yeah he became another hunt
but understanding the body well exactly but
understanding the body well exactly but
seeing that actually this is
there's nothing to be conceited about or
feeling theater and kind of either it is
as i said
your sense of self your conceit is like
it's something your eye doesn't even
know about
yet here you are you know all important
or all unimportant all afraid but your
own body
is not aware of you look how wonderful i
am on account of this thing that is not
mine yeah yeah that has its own cause
that i kind of know but i ignore because
i'm intoxicated with the pleasure that i
get momentarily from it
that's why you develop these views as
well if the if the if the
if the if the if the
conceit and central pleasures were not
pleasant nobody would be conceited or vain
nobody would be conceited or vain
but you get pleasure on account of it
you take pleasure for granted you put
the pleasure first you put the pleasure
as the basis of your whole experience
and then you could be witnessing
unpleasant things and not see the nature
of it because you refuse to allow the
order to change
you still put the pleasure first
you refuse to give it up
your body can be deteriorating breaking
down and you still remain attracted to
bodily pleasures because you refuse to
put them second you refuse to see the
bodies first because now it's too
unpleasant as well to admit that the
longer you admit the longer you refuse
to admit it the harder it will be to do
it later
because you're becoming more and more
dependent on that wrong order
practically speaking the burden is
getting heavier
and it's crushing you more and more and
if you couldn't give it up so easily
when it was relatively light
so don't wait till it's too late in
other words
because the intoxication
grows the more you engage with it the more
the more you engage with it the more
intoxicated you become
the harder it will be to sober up